Ladakh is at a very very high altitude, it is
बहुत बहुत हाइट पर है
16 times higher than Delhi, there is a
लद्दाख दिल्ली से 16 गुना ज्यादा हाइट में
shortage of everything here, there is a shortage of water,
है हर चीज की यहां कमी है पानी की कमी
people should not have it here, still
है यहां लोगों को नहीं होना चाहिए फिर भी
in every house of our Ladakh, potatoes are
हैं हमारे लद्दाख के हर घर में आलू को छ
kept underground for six months, a 6
महीने तक अंडरग्राउंड रखा जाता है एक 6
feet 7 feet long
फीट 7 फीट लंबा
Ghaddar, Radish, Turnip, everything is kept for six months so that
घड्डर मूली शलगम सब रखा जाता है छ महीनों
it does not get spoiled by snow, the Ladha people
तक ताकि वह बर्फ से खराब ना हो लदा वाला
keep it like this, imagine that it
हर ऐसे रखता है सोचो कि पूरे साल में बस
rains only for 10 to 12 days in the whole year, it is
10 से 12 दिन की बारिश होती है यहां
so dry here, the highest place of
पर इतना सूखा है द हाईएस्ट प्लेस ऑफ
India,
इंडिया
Hello Sir, we stayed in Ladakh, in the house of this cute local
हेलो सर लद्दाख में हम रहे इन क्यूट लोकल
couple,
कपल के घर
this thick roti of Ladakh is made of Gad only,
में ये लद्दाख की मोटी रोटी है गड़ से ही
but it is very thick,
बनी हुई है बट बहुत मोटी है जैसे हमारी
four times the thickness of our normal roti,
नॉर्मल रोटी होगी ना उसकी चार गुना इसका
and this is dal, the normal mixed
मोटापा है और ये दाल है नॉर्मल जो मिक्स
dal, we are currently staying in a homestay, if
दाल होती है हम लोग अभी होम स्टे में रुके
you see this room, it is like a normal
हैं यह कमरा आप देखोगे तो जैसे नॉर्मली
local house, room
लोकल्स का घर होता है कमरा होता है वैसा
and right in the middle of it, there is a traditional
ही है और उसके ठीक बीच में जो ट्रेडिशनल
heater,
हीटर है वो भी लगा रखा
because Ladakh is a desert, so
है क्योंकि लद्दाख एक डेजर्ट है तो यहां
farming cannot be done here for six months.  So
पर खेती 6 महीने तक हो ही नहीं पाती तो
that's why these local solutions, local ways of
इसीलिए ये लोकल सॉल्यूशन लोकल वेज ऑफ
living, help the people here to
लिविंग ही हेल्प करते हैं यहां के लोगों
eat and live.
को खाने और जीने
If you see the food here, you must have
में यहां का अगर आप खाना देखें तो आपने
seen
देखा होगा यहां
Thuppa here, what are you making now? I have just made Thuppa, or
थुपा अभी आप क्या बना रहे हो अभी मैं थुपा
take Gaja, this vegetable, so many vegetables have been prepared
ले यह सब्जी पूरा इतना सारा सब्जी तयार
[Music]
[संगीत]
When you drink boiled soup, then one glass of
रखा जब आप उबला हुआ सूप पीते हैं तो एक गल
soup gives heat to your whole body, so
सूप का आपके पूरे शरीर को गर्मी दे तो
how efficient it is, you can see everything goes into
कितना एफिशिएंट है आप देख सकते हैं हर चीज
it, so a nutritious meal in a single
उसमें जाता है तो एक पौष्टिक आहार एक ही
vessel
बर्तन
because the resources are very limited here, so
में क्योंकि यहां पर रिसोर्सेस बहुत कम है
we cannot make three pots on three stoves,
तो हम तीन तीन पतीले तीन तीन चूलो पर नहीं
ah one more is happening very well,
कर सकते हैं अ एक और बहुत अच्छा हो रहा है
please thank
प्लीज थैंक
you, very good, very good, it looks
यू बहुत अच्छा बहुत अच्छा बहुत अच्छा ये
very healthy, it seems like he is eating something good, he is eating something
बहुत हेल्दी लग ऐसा लग रहा है कि अच्छा
healthy, what is in it,
चीज खा रहा है हेल्दी चीज खा रहा है इसमें
in this Ladakh he says like beer, like
इस लद में बोलता है जैसे बियर
local beer of
जसे ंग लोकल बियर ऑफ
Ladakh
लद्दाख
[Music]
[संगीत]
wow and
वाओ और
our drunkards have come, it's so tasty, I have
बेवड़े हमारे आ गए हैं इतना टेस्टी मैंने
this beer, it's beer, it's so tasty, I have
ये बियर है बियर है इतना टेस्टी बियर
not had beer,
मैंने नहीं पिया
how is it, very good, it's like a tree,
है कैसा है बहुत अच्छा ये तड़ी जैसा तड़ी
not like a tree, the food of Ladakh here is very good  It
जैसा नहीं यहां लद्दाख का खाना तो बहुत ही
was nutritious but
न्यूट्रिशस था लेकिन हमारे शहरों में
due to our changing lifestyle in our cities, people
हमारी बदलती लाइफ स्टाइल की वजह से लोगों
's health is getting affected, so today
की हेल्थ अफेक्ट हो रही है इसलिए आज
10 crore people in India are diabetic, which means that there is
इंडिया में 10 करोड़ लोग डायबिटिक है मतलब
a diabetic patient in every third house,
हर तीसरे घर में एक डायबिटीज का पेशेंट
whom this BeatO
मिलेगा जिनकी हेल्प करता है ये बीटो
glucometer helps. With this, you can check your
ग्लूकोमीटर इससे आप कहीं भी और कभी भी
sugar levels or those of your family members anywhere and anytime.
अपने परिवार वालों के या अपने शुगर लेवल्स
This is the first
चेक कर सकते हो यह इंडिया का पहला ऐसा
glucometer in India that
ग्लूकोमीटर है जो डायरेक्टली यब के थ्रू
connects directly to the phone through the app. Just
फोन से कनेक्ट हो जाता है बस अपने फोन पे
install BeatO app on your phone, then insert this testing
बटो पप इंस्टॉल करना है फिर इस टेस्टिंग
strip in the glucometer,
स्ट्रिप को ग्लूकोमीटर में इंसर्ट करना है
then prick your cleaned finger with this lancing tool
फिर इस लैंसिंग टूल से अपनी साफ की हुई
and see, in just 10
उंगली को प्रिक करना है और यह देखो बस 10
seconds I got my results and
सेकंड्स में मुझे मेरे रिजल्ट्स मिल गए और
found out that my sugar level is slightly
पता चला कि मेरा ही शुगर लेवल थोड़ा सा
high. Now I can share these results with
हाई है अब इन रिजल्ट्स को मैं बटो एप से
my family or top doctors of India through the BeatO app itself.
ही अपनी फैमिली या फिर इंडिया के टॉप
This is not
डॉक्टर्स से शेयर कर सकती हू यह ना
amazon.es and it is also a certified glucometer, there is
amazon.es और यह आओ सर्टिफाइड ग्लूकोमीटर
no battery problem and there is
भी है ना कोई बैटरी का झंझट और लाइफ टाइम
also a lifetime warranty and with this you will
वारंटी भी है और इसी के साथ आपको 25
also get 25 strips and 25 lancets, so much
स्ट्रिप्स और 25 लांसेट्स भी मिलेंगे इतना
for free  Only ₹ 4499, so you can
सब कुछ फॉर ओनली ₹ 4499 तो इसको आप भी
gift this to your parents and grandparents
अपने पेरेंट्स और ग्रैंडपेरेंट्स को गिफ्ट
and with the butt-knowledge provider feature, you
कर सकते हो और बट ए के केयर गिवर फीचर के
can manage their sugar levels. The
साथ उनके शुगर लेवल्स मैनेज कर सकते हो
link for this is in the description below. Now let's go
इसका लिंक नीचे डिस्क्रिप्शन में है अब
back to the
चलते हैं बैक टू द
[Music]
[संगीत]
video. In our Ladakh's capital, 66% of the
वीडियो हमारे लद्दाख की कैपिटल में 66 पर
population follows Buddhism
पॉपुलेशन बुद्धिज्म फॉलो करती
[Prashasa]
[प्रशंसा]
and this Shanti Stupa reflects this
है और इसी पीसफुल रिलीजन को दर्शाता है यह
peaceful religion
शांति स्तूप
and if you come here, you will feel that peace, you will
और यहां आओगे ना तो फील होगा वो शांति वो
feel that peace
पीस फील
because there is a lot of peace
होगी क्योंकि बहुत शांति
[Music]
[संगीत]
Right now, where I am standing, it
है अभी मैं जहां पर खड़ी हूं वो एक्चुअली
is actually a frozen river, I mean, water is flowing under this ice
फ्रोजन रिवर है एक मतलब इसी आइस के नीचे
and it has frozen so much that it has turned into
पानी बह रहा है और वो इतना जम चुका है कि
ice
एकदम बर्फ बन चुका है आइस बन चुका है
[Music]
[संगीत]
[Prashasa]
[प्रशंसा]
You can see this ice, even if you hit it a little, it will
आप देख सकते हो य आइस आप इसको थोड़े से भी
not break and people are ice skating on it, it is
मारोगे नहीं टूटेगा य और उसी में लोग आइस
not easy to walk on it, people
हैं मलब इससे चलना इजी नहीं है
come from outside also to skate,
बाहर से भी आते हैं य लोग स्केटिंग करने
yes ma'am, people come from everywhere and
हां जी मैम हर जगह से आते हैं और गांव
skating is going on in every village as well. Right now, the
गांव में भी स्केटिंग चल रहा है अभी नदी
whole game is going on in the rivers and streams
नालियों में पूरे गेम चल रहा
[Music]
[संगीत]
Yesterday, Ladakh  How was it made is the most
है कल लद्दाख बना कैसे ना यह सबसे
interesting thing, millions of years ago the
इंटरेस्टिंग चीज है करोड़ों सालों पहले
Ural plate collided with the Indian plate and then the
यूरेज प्लेट इंडियन प्लेट से टकराई और तब
mastic mountain
बनी है मस्टिक माउंटेन
Himalayas were formed and because of these Himalayas
हिमालया और इन्हीं हिमालयाज की वजह से
a rain shadow area is created here
यहां पर एक रेन शैडो एरिया क्रिएट हो जाता
due to which the rain clouds are
है जिसकी वजह से रेन वाले बादल यहां पर
unable to reach here, so now where will the water come from,
पहुंच नहीं पाते तो अब पानी कहां से आएगा
for this the people here have come
इसके लिए यहां के लोगों ने कई सारे
up with many innovative solutions for years
इनोवेटिव सॉल्यूशंस निकाले हैं सालों
[Music] I
[संगीत]
mean it looks like a mountain made of ice
से मतलब ऐसा लग रहा है बर्फ से बना हुआ
[Music]
[संगीत]
and this is not naturally formed, it has been made
ये और ये नेचुरली नहीं बना है इसे
artificially, it is man-made, it
आर्टिफिशली बना है लोग मैन मेड है य ना
looks beautiful, it is not small, this
सुंदर लग रहा है छोटा नहीं है
Ice Tapa behind us has been
य यह हमारे पीछे आइस तपा बना है
formed out of helplessness
एंड जो आई तपा जो बना है वह आउट ऑफ मजबूरी
because there is a lot of water shortage
की वजह से क्योंकि पानी के किल्लत बहुत है
in Ladakh right now we are Ice Tapa's
में अभी हम लोग है आइस ूपा के
[Music]
[संगीत]
Oh they have been places who
ओ दे हैव बीन प्लेसेस जिन्होंने इसी डोम
built a cafe inside this dome, it's a nice cafe inside an Ice
के अंदर एक कैफे बनाया इ नाइस कैफे इनसाइड
Tapa. To make an Ice Tapa, first of all
ूपा आई ूपा बनाने में सबसे पहले लकड़ी का
a structure of wood is made, it is the wood
एक ढांचा बनाते हैं यह वो लकड़ियां है
from which a complete mold structure is made and through an
जिनसे एक पूरा मोल्ड ढांचा बना है और एक
underground pipe,
अंडरग्राउंड पाइप लेकर बहुत सारी ग्लेशियर
water is brought from many glaciers
से पानी लेके आते
and  They place that pipe right in the middle of this mould.
हैं और उनको उस पाइप को इस मोल्ड के ठीक
Now the water from the glacier
हैं अब ग्लेशियर का पानी जो होता है वह
comes so fast that it flows straight out of the pipe
इतना तेज आता है कि पाइप से सीधा पानी
and then it meets
निकलता है और फिर उसकी मुलाकात होती है
-20 - 30 degree Celsius, so the water
-20 - 30 डिग्री सेल्सियस से तो पानी एकदम
freezes completely and then these big
जम जाता है और फिर बनते हैं ये बड़े आइस
mountains of ice are formed, which is like the biggest storm that has come
पहाड़ विच इज लाइक द बिगेस्ट तूफा दैट हैज
last year, it was built only by Thatch, which
कम लास्ट ईयर ओनली ताच ने बनाया था जिसने
conserved 13 million litres of water. This
13 मिलियन लीटर का वाटर कंजर्व किया था ये
complete structure that you are seeing was
जो आप स्ट्रक्चर पूरा देख रहे हो ये 40
built in 40 days, it will become bigger now, it will be
दिन में बना है अभी और बड़ा होगा अभी तो
quite big now, so why is it that
काफी बड़ा होगा तो क्यों ऐसा होता है कि
so many problem-solving
लद्दाख से इतनी सारी प्रॉब्लम सॉल्विंग
solvers come out of Ladakh? Because if there are a lot of problems then there will be a
सॉल्वर्स निकल के आते हैं क्योंकि
lot of solvers too. The
प्रॉब्लम्स बहुत है तो सॉल्वर्स भी बहुत
going gets tough, it gets tough. I guess the
होंगे न द गोइंग गेट्स टफ टफ गेट गोइंग आई
lifestyle makes you think that
गेस हार्ड लाइफस्टाइल मेक्स यू थिंक टियर
everything is easily available in tier one cities,
वन सिटीज में सब कुछ आसानी से मिल जाता है
everything is there, there is no need of innovation,
सब कुछ है देर ज नो नीड ऑफ इनोवेशन ना मीस
your lifestyle is pretty easy here
योर लाइफ स्टाइल इज प्रेट इजी यहां लद्दाख
in Ladakh, because there used to be so many problems earlier, and
में क्योंकि पहले इतने प्रॉब्लम्स हुआ
even now there are so many problems, so that
करते थे इतने अभी भी प्रॉब्लम्स है तो दैट
would make you think.  What can we do differently?
वुड मेक यू थिंक कि हम लोग अलग से क्या कर
For example, in down plains, we
सकते हैं फॉर एग्जांपल इन डाउन प्लेनस वी
use toilets, right? We do our business. We
यूज टॉयलेट्स राइट वी डू आवर बिजनेस वी
flush and then we forget about it. What happens to the
फ्लश एंड देन वी फॉरगेट अबाउट इट व्हाट
stuff that we flush? In Ladakh, we
हैपेंस टू द स्टफ दैट वी फ्लश इन लद्दाख
have dry composting
वी हैव ड्राई कंपोस्टिंग
toilets. This is the only toilet in India that does
टॉयलेट्स यह भारत का ऐसा टॉयलेट जिसमें
not use water. You will
पानी नहीं यूज होता हमारे लद्दाख में हर
find this toilet in every home in Ladakh. Like
घर में यह टॉयलेट मिलेगा जैसे वेस्टर्न
in western toilets, when we defecate,
टॉयलेट्स में जब हम टॉयलेट करते हैं तो
they have to be taken to septic tanks.
उन्हें सेप्टिक टैंक्स में ले जाना पड़ता
But here,
है पर यहां पर ह्यूमन टॉयलेट से ही
fertilizer is produced from human toilets. People defecate on the first floor. The waste is collected
फर्टिलाइजर बनता है इस फर्स्ट फ्लोर में
below.
लोग टॉयलेट करते हैं जो नीचे कलेक्ट होती
Grass or dung is put in it so that the
है इसमें घास या गोबर डाली जाती है ताकि
material collected below becomes compost properly.
नीचे कलेक्ट हुआ सामान अच्छे से खाद बन
After years, this manure is collected
जाए सालों बाद इस खाद को कलेक्ट किया जाता
and used in the farms here. The
है और यहां के फार्म्स में यूज किया जाता
whole of India can learn from Ladakh
है लद्दाख से पूरी इंडिया सीख सकती है कि
how to save water
कैसे पानी को बचाना
[Music]
[संगीत]
And still, there is no smell in this toilet.
चाहिए और फिर भी इस टॉयलेट में कोई स्मेल
Oh, this bunch of spinach, this bunch of coriander, coriander too.
ओ यह लद पालक की यह लद व धनिया धनिया भी
Yes, yes, this coriander, this
हां जी हां जी यह
mint, these strawberries. Gradually, everything will grow
धनि यह पुदीना ये स्ट्रॉबरी धीरे-धीरे सब
big. They are small. Right now,
बड़ा हो जाए छोटा छोटा है अभी तो छोटा
we are small.  We are not proud of the fact that they make ice tops or
छोटा है हम जो यह आइस टूप बनाते हैं या
solar buildings.
सोलर बिल्डिंग बनाते हैं इस पर हमें गर्व
This is not a big solution.
नहीं है यह कोई बड़े सलूशन नहीं है इससे
What can we change with this because the root of these problems is
हम क्या बदलेंगे क्योंकि इन समस्याओं का
here. No, these are small fixes.
जड़ यहां है नहीं यह छोटे-छोटे फिक्सस हैं
Their roots are in Delhi, London, Mumbai,
इनके जड़ हैं दिल्ली में लंदन में मुंबई
Beijing. If the people there live a little
में बेजिंग में वहां के लोग अगर थोड़ी
simply, we will be able to live.
सादगी से जिए तो हम जी
[Music] What will
[संगीत]
you tell people about the
पाएंगे आप लोगों को क्या बताओगे कि लद्दाख
good things in Ladakh? There is
में लद्दाख में क्या अच्छी चीज है लद्दाख
snow to see in Ladakh, there are
में बरफ देखने के लिए फ्रूट देखने के लिए
apples to see, there is fruit here, there is nothing green here right now in
सेब है सब कुछ है यहां पे फ्रूट अभी तो
winter.
विंटर में कुछ नहीं है हरा हरा नहीं है
Everything will look good at my house. So all of you come, I will
मेरे वो घर सब अच्छा लगेगा तो सब आ जाना
serve you a lot. Take a break or take a
मे बहुत सेवा करेगा ठीक है ले थक य
break because the altitude is so high here. That's
जुले क्योंकि यहां पे एल्टीट्यूड इतना हाई
why we were already taking this medicine Diamox
है इसलिए यह दवाई डायमॉक्स हम लोग ऑलरेडी
two days ago before leaving.
दो दिन पहले निकलने के खाते जा रहे थे एक
We have also taken a permit because we have
परमिट भी लिया है हमने क्योंकि हम लोग
come to Ladakh in the off-season. So we have to
लद्दाख ऑफ सीजन में आए हैं तो गवर्नमेंट
take a permit from the government site. No
साइट से एक परमिट भी लेना पड़ता है कोई
prepaid phone works here. Only the
प्रीपेड फोन यहां पे चलता नहीं है सिर्फ
local Ladakhi SIM works
लद्दाखी जो लोकल सिम होता है वो चलता है
or postpaid, that too only on
या फिर पोस्ट पेड वो भी सिर्फ
airtelhellotunes.in.
airtelhellotunes.in
I am here. Thank
हमा में में थैंक
you, good.
यू गुड
[Music]
[संगीत]
Afternoon what is this mike, what is
आफ्टरनून य क्या है माइक क्या होता है
this, tell
इससे इस
me what do you want to become, you are an engineer,
मोह इंजीनियर इंजीनियर बनाते
tell me your ring, show it to the camera,
रिंग बताओ आपकी रिंग वहां पर दिखाओ कैमरे
what do you want to become when you grow up, I want to join the
दिखाओ आपको क्या बनना है बड़े हो के मुझे
army when I grow up, I want to
बड़े हो के आर्मी बनना है आर्मी में जाना
join the army, so why do you want to join the army, I like the
है आपको तो आपको जॉइन क्यों करनी है आर्मी
army very much, what does the army do, it
मुझे आर्मी बहुत अच्छी लगती है आमी क्या
keeps our country safe and why is the security of the country important so that all the
कते है और देश की सुरक्षा क्यों जरूरी है
Hindus and Muslims in our India
जो हमारे इंडिया में जितने भी हिंदू
remain safe, that's why
मुस्लिम स वो सब सुरक्षित रहे इसलिए
Kali
काली
[praise]
[प्रशंसा]
Jai ma'am, I am a primary level teacher of this school,
जय मैम मैं इस स्कूल का एक प्राइमरी लेवल
so I have a lot of
का एक टीचर हूं तो इनके साथ मुझे बहुत
affection with these small children, that's why
लगाव है इन छोटे बच्चों के साथ तो इसलिए
I am in the class, now I am making
मैं क्लास ही ही है तो मैं अभी जो
NIPHM so that
एनआईपीएचएम
our children get the basic
ताक हमारे बच्चे जो है उनको जो बेसिक जो
concept, um, I also
कांसेप्ट हैम वो आ जाए उम बो भी मैंने
made this, so we keep it in it,
बनाया इस के तो हम इसको इसमें रखते हैं
ma'am, skip and keep it in this way, now if we let the
मैम स्किप करके इसम रखते इस तरह से अब
child pick it up through this, then the child will
बच्चे को इस जरिए उठाने देते तो बच्चे य
trap it from this, so this
से इसको ट्रैप करेंगे तो इसको आ गया
triangle will be matching with it,
ट्रायंगल इसके साथ मैचिंग
you saw the three idiots, in that Aamir Khan's
करेंगे थ्री इडिट देखी आपने उसम आमिर खान
character was as passionate and
का जो कैरेक्टर था व जितना जुनूनी और
passionate, he was for education, in the same way  There are
पैशनेट था ना एजुकेशन के लिए वैसे ही
other teachers in Ladakh too, we got to know this after coming here
लद्दाख के बाकी टीचर्स भी है यह हमें यहां
and what do you want your children to
चला और आप क्या चाहते हो कि आपके बच्चे
become when they grow up, if everything happens according to my wish, then
बड़े होकर क्या बने अगर मेरे चाहने से सब
I would like that
कुछ होगा ना तो मैं तो यही चाहूंगा कि
my children
मेरे बच्चे ना मेरे बच्चे इंसान
become human beings, when children become human beings,
बने जब इंसान बच्चे बनते हैं ना बाकी सब
they become everything else on their own because I have
कुछ वो खुद बन जाते हैं क्योंकि मैंने
stolen dialogues from many films,
बहुत सारी फिल्मों के डायलॉग चुरा के
unless they become a good citizen, they will not be
लाया अगर जब तक वो एक अच्छा सिटीजन नहीं
able to become a good doctor, they will not be
बनेगा तो अच्छा डॉक्टर नहीं बन पाओगे
able to become a good engineer, in school they
अच्छा इंजीनियर नहीं बन पाओगे स्कूल में
teach on smart boards,
तो स्मार्ट बोर्ड के बोर्ड प पढ़ाते हैं
these children have got university level facilities, so
यूनिवर्सिटी के लेवल के फैसिलिटी इन
we talk about this every day in the classes that
बच्चों को मिला है तो हम हर रोज क्लासों
such good facilities have come for you people, if you people do
इतना अच्छे फैसिलिटी आए हैं अगर आप लोग
not study then you people are unfortunate, I
नहीं पढ़ेंगे तो आप लोग बदबख्त हैं मैं
mean that I myself have
ऐसा मतलब यह चाहती हूं कि मैं खुद अभी पढ़
come here after studying to teach them, in the same
के यहां प इनको पढ़ाने के लिए आई हूं इसी
way, serve your community,
तरह अपनी कौम की खिदमत करें मां-बाप की
serve your parents, serve others,
खिदमत करें दूसरों की खिदमत करें ऐसे एक
become a worthy person, this is enough for a person,
लायक इंसान बने यही काफी है एक इंसान के
what a thing
लिए क्या बात
[Music] It
[संगीत]
felt good to see that in such a unique
है अच्छा लगा यार ये देख के कि इतनी यूनिक
place, even in the highest place of India, there is
जगह में भी इंडिया के हाईएस्ट प्लेस में
a school like this  Which
भी एक स्कूल है ऐसा स्कूल जो विंटर्स में
runs even in winters, in such extreme cold, there is a
भी चलता है इतनी ज्यादा ठंड में है ऐसा
school which gives hope that no matter
स्कूल जो ये आशा देता है कि चाहे नेचर
how many difficulties the nature gives you, the spirit should never
तुम्हें कितनी भी मुश्किलें दे जज्बे कभी
diminish,
कम नहीं होने
Lord, I thank you for the sunshine, thank you
चाहिए लर्ड आई थैंक यू फॉर सनशाइन थैंक यू
for not thank you for joy, thank you for pain, it's
फॉर न थैंक यू फॉर जॉय थैंक यू फॉर पेन
a beautiful day, it's a
इट्स अ ब्यूटीफुल डे ब्यूटीफुल डे इट्स अ
beautiful
ब्यूटीफुल
day, don't fear and fight, let us unite, we get one
डे डोंट फर्स एंड फाइट लेट अस यूनाइट वी
like so let's make it right, it's a
गट वन लाइक सो लेट्स मेक इट राइट इट्स अ
beautiful day, beautiful day, it's a
ब्यूटीफुल डे ब्यूटीफुल डे इट्स अ
beautiful
ब्यूटीफुल
day and remember to check out BeatO
डे एंड रिमेंबर टू चेक आउट बीटो
Glucometer, the link for which is given in the description below.
ग्लूकोमीटर जिसका लिंक नीचे डिस्क्रिप्शन